An Inventory to the Pardee Lowe papers, 1911-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
SEADAG
Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group
SEAMES
Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat
SEATO
Southeast Asia Treaty Organization
UNESCO
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
USAID
United States Agency for International Development
USAFR
United States Air Force Reserves
USEFC (also USEF China)
United States Educational Foundation in China (Fulbright Program)
USIA
United States Information Agency (e.g. Box 340)
USIS
United States Information Service (US Department of State)
YMCA
Yound Men's Christian Association. Also used as an abbreviation for Chinese YMCA, the separate YMCA facilities for people of Chinese descent
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Unesco.; International education.; East Asia.; Chinese Americans.; United States Dept. of State.; China--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--China.; Chinatown (San Francisco, Calif.); San Francisco (Calif.); Taiwan.
Additional Indexing Terms
Golden Gate International Exposition (1939-1940--San Francisco, Calif.); Stanford University.; Stanford University. Alumni Association.; Counterintelligence.; Cold War.; Taiwan Advocates.; Institute of Pacific Relations.; Institute of Pacific Relations (6th conference: 1936: Yosemite, Calif.); Institute of Pacific Relations--History.; YMCA.; Young Men's Christian Association.; International House (Berkeley, Calif.); International House (New York, N.Y.); International House (New York, N.Y.)--Alumni and alumnae.; China-Burma-India Veterans Association.; Unted States. Army.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1931-1933.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; Chinatown (Oakland, Calif.)
Collection Contents
- Original folders have been retained; folder titles may not match the contents
- Department of State files, 1956-1980s (Box 1)
  - State Department intelligence publications (Box 1)
  - Typescript reports (Box 1)
  - UNESCO printed reports (Box 1)
  - Printed materials on education, especially adult education, employability, and vocational training, 1956-1980s (Box 1)
  - Materials relating to 1973 National Adult Education Think Tank Project (Box 1)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 2-9.)
  Printed materials related to UNESCO, education, linguistics, and China trade
- UNESCO Printed materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
  - Materials related to conventions on adult literacy, UNESCO and USAID (Box 3)
  - World Congress of Ministers of Education statistical report (Box 3)
  - Congressional publications, such as hearings before Congressional subcommittees (Box 3)
  - Asian Development Bank (Box 3)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare in cooperation with Dept of State (Box 3)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (Box 3)
  - Japan Society, NY (Box 3)
  - Printed guides to encourage import trade to U.S. and use of labor (Box 3)
- UNESCO Printed materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 4)
  - Tanzania textbook, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Typescript proposal for fundamental curriculum for illiterates (Box 4)
- UNESCO Printed materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 5)
- Printed materials related to Congressional appropriations, 1960s-1970. (Box 6-7)
  Includes material related to Department of State, USAID, and the Department of Defense
- Asian Development Bank, Asia Agricultural Survey, Japan: University of Tokyo Press and University of Washington Press, 1969 (Box 7)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1980s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 8-9.)
  - Department of State printed policy briefings, news releases, and other materials, some marked not for public circulation (Box 8-9.)
  - UN economic reports and other printed material, including related to USAID and to teaching Chinese (Box 8-9.)
- Report from U.S. to UN (Box 9)
- Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR) documents, 1935-1936 (Box 10)
- GGIE Pacific house planning committee files,, and related clippings, 1939 (Box 10)
- Printed materials (Box 10)
- Mainly printed materials, 1930s-1960s (Box 11)
  - Guidebooks, related to Korea and Japan, and to relations between U.S. and Asian counties (Box 11)
  - Universities Field Staff report, 1956 (Box 11)
- IPR Chinatown survey files, undated, 1930s. (Box 12)
  Consists of San Francisco Chinatown "Survey Work" notebook with entries for each address, street by street, holographic, in English and Chinese, undated, made from 1933 appointment book
- San Francisco Chinatown subject files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 12)
  Mainly clippings and San Francisco Chinatown newsletters and flyers, in English and in Chinese
- San Francisco Chinatown subject files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 13)
  Clippings, ephemera, and printed material, some related to San Francisco Chinatown
- Subject files, 1960s-1990s. (Box 14)
  Includes clippings
- Bulletins of the Institute of Current World Affairs (Box 14)
- Subject files, 1979-1983 (Box 15-16.)
- Chinatown subject files, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
- Subject files, 1970s-1990s (bulk 1990s) (Box 18)
- Chinatown subject files, 1970s-1990s (bulk 1990s) (Box 18)
- Subject files, 1990s (Box 19)
- Chinatown subject files, 1990s (Box 19)
- Subject files, 1990s (Box 20)
- Clippings, 1990s (Box 21)
- Printed materials related to UNESCO, 1950s-1960s (Box 21)
- Printed material largely related to foreign policy, communism, and the USSR, 1950s-1970s (Box 22)
- UNESCO Printed material, 1960s-1970s (Box 23-27)
- "Asian Draft Model," UNESCO report for limited distribution, 1965 September 10 (Box 23-27.)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s (Box 28)
- Documents and notes related to Lowe's work on UNESCO, 1960s-1970s (Box 29-32)
- Tatung University teaching files, 1980s-1990s (Box 32)
- Subject files, 1990s (Box 33)
- Clippings, 1990s (Box 34)
- Clippings, 1990s (Box 35-36.)
- State Department bulletins (Box 35-36.)
- Printed materials (Box 35-36.)
- Tatung Company prospectus (Box 35-36.)
- UNESCO work files, 1960s-1970s (Box 37-39.)
- Clippings in various large envelopes from Taipei, 1980s (Box 40)
- Future Development of the San Francisco Bay Area, 1960-2020, U.S. Dept of Commerce (prepared for U.S. Army Corps of Engineers) report with accompanying oversize full-color maps (Box 40)
- UNESCO work files, typescript and holographic, including speech or formal memo draft and position paper draft with edits, 1960s-1970s (Box 41)
- Documents related to budgeting and computerized report making, some holographic, probably 1980s (Box 41)
- Printed materials on "Free China" (Box 41)
- Business and educational serials (Box 42)
- Financial investment service printed materials and annual reports (Box 42)
- Cultural Affairs Attaché, U.S. Embassy, Taipei, Taiwan materials, 1960s (Box 43)
  - List of diplomatic personnel (Box 43)
  - Phone directories (Box 43)
  - U.S. Information Service directories for Taipei with English and Chinese name, phone, and address (Box 43)
  - Printed materials (Box 43)
- Foo Hsing Opera Troup performances in support of Free China album of clippings, telegrams, and photos, 1962-1963 (Box 43)
- Cultural Affairs Attaché files, 1960s (Box 44)
- Clippings and printed material, 1960s-1980s (Box 44)
- Subject files, clippings, and notes, 1980s (Box 45-49.)
- State Department bulletins (Box 45-49.)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1969-1974 (Box 50-54.)
- Reports and position papers (Box 50-54.)
- Reports related to advisory committees and recruitment of U.S. nationals arranged in subject files, including subject files relating to literacy (Box 52)
- Anita Lowe letters, cards, bulk mail, and documents mainly relating to religion, including bulletins of the 5th Chinese Congress on World Evangelization, 1996, and holographic notes (Box 52)
- PhD dissertation files, 1950s. (Box 55)
  Includes early dissertation drafts, typescript, and correspondence with advisory Professor George Lantzeff, 1952
- Subject file, "1945-November,", 1935-1976 (Box 55)
- Printed materials, clippings, and financial company mailings, mid 1990s (Box 55)
- Unsorted clippings, 1990s (Box 56)
- Printed materials, 1930s (Box 57)
- PhD studies files, 1950s (Box 57)
- Chinese PhD examination notes, holographic and typescript (Box 57)
- Clippings, 1986, and holographic notes (Box 57)
- Printed material related to the UN,1950, and to Chiang Kai-shek (Box 57)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s, including folders divided by month (1945 April-October) (Box 58)
- PhD student papers in preparation of dissertation (Box 58)
- Joseph McCarthy investigations research file, especially related to Owen Lattimore, including holographic and typescript material and clippings (Box 58)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 59)
- PhD student papers relevant to dissertation, subject files, copy of draft for volume I, 1950s (Box 59)
- "Outline of Leading Chinese Newspapers" by region, typescript drafts (Box 59)
- News stories from the U.S. Information Service (such as "Hoover War Library Described" 1946 January 28) (Box 59)
- Translations of Chinese newspaper stories (Box 59)
- Notes and printed programs from the Asilomar Conference on China, December 1949 (Box 59)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 60)
- Correspondence with advisory professors (Box 60)
- USAFR files, Lowe, Maj. Pardee, U.S. Air Force Reserve, 1950s-1964 (Box 60)
- "How to Clip the New York Times for Intelligence Items on the Soviet Union" training for work with Russian news articles, typescript lesson plan, 1954 or later (Box 60)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s, folders divided by month, 1950 February-March (Box 61)
- Clippings (Box 61)
- Printed material characterizing the Soviet Union and Taiwan, especially with regard to education and culture, 1930s-1980s (Box 62-63)
- Items relating to the emerging field of Asian American studies (Box 62-63)
- Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 64-65.)
- Greeting cards to Anita Lowe, with holographic messages in English and Chinese and miscellaneous mailings (Box 64-65.)
- Department of State Education Officer files (Box 66)
- Printed material on education by UNESCO, 1960s (Box 66)
- "Study Group on Education and Nation-Building Annual Report 1967-1968," Ann Arbor: U of Michigan (Box 66)
- Department of State Education Officer files printed materials, mainly on education, and education's role in military readiness, 1960s-1970s (Box 67)
- Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 68-70)
- Church programs (Box 71)
- Clippings and holographic notes (Box 71-74.)
- Printed materials (Box 71-74.)
- State Department bulletins, 1970s-1980s (Box 71-74.)
- Subject files, 1979-1983 (Box 75-79.)
  - China (Box 75-79.)
  - Chinese studies (Box 75-79.)
  - Chinese Americans (Box 75-79.)
  - Africa (Box 75)
  - Soviet Union (Box 76-77.)
  - Taiwan (Box 79)
  - U.S. politics and ethnic relations and investments (Box 78-79.)
- Miscellaneous desk documents, 1980s, including financial documents and notes of Anita Lowe (Box 80-81.)
- Subject file material, early 1990s. Some labeled envelopes of clippings (Box 81-82.)
- "The Story of Dr. Burke Liang Sun (November 30, 1908 - May 16, 1990)," Pearl Shih Hua Sun Nye and William George Nye (Box 81-82.)
- Correspondence with Pearl Shih Hua Sun Nye and William George Nye (Box 81)
- Subject files, 1960s-1980s. (Box 85-92)
- "Manual for LS Oral Interview Workshops," by Pardee Lowe, Jr., Language School, 1980 June, sponsored by the CIA and Defense Language Institute (Box 85-92)
- USSR Subject file (Box 91)
- "University Revolt" subject files, 1968-1971 (Box 92)
- Biographical material, including from Lowe attending Stanford University (Box 93)
- Completed class registration cards, 1926-1929 (Box 93)
- Correspondence, 1940s, includes Schering, Nanking, correspondence (Box 93)
- Stanford Alumni file (Box 93)
- Nanking files, 1948 (Box 93)
- "University Revolt" subject file, 1960s-1970s (Box 93)
- Correspondence, 1940s. (Box 94)
  Includes typescript copy of military record report, as counterintelligence officer
- Biographical material, Stanford transcript and documents relating to loans from Stanford (Box 94)
- Subject files, 1960s-1970s (Box 94)
- Appointment books, 1934, 1935, and undated (Box 95)
- Subject files 1960s-1970 (Box 95)
- Datebook pages with holographic annotations, 1933 and undated (Box 96)
- Draft writings related to San Francisco Chinatown with annotations, undated (Box 96)
- Notes, typescript and holographic, 1940s-1960s (Box 96)
- San Francisco printed materials, 1930-1934 (Box 96)
- Collected material in support of writing (Box 97)
- Clippings and printed material, 1920s-1930s and 1960s-1970s (Box 97)
- San Francisco Chinatown ephemera, includes printed materials on Chinese Hospital, San Francisco, 1920s (Box 97)
- Printed material related to China. (Box 97)
  Includes illustrated pamphlets promoting Chinese Industrial Co-operatives, possibly 1930s
- Phi Lamda fraternity files, 1950s-1970s (Box 98)
- Printed materials on publishing, writing and literature, some received at Institute of Pacific Relations, 1930s (Box 98)
- Correspondence, 1930s (Box 99)
- Newsletters and other notices related to San Francisco's Chinese YMCA and the Chinese American Citizens Alliance (C.A.C.A.) (Box 99)
- Hand-sewn holographic Chinese record books, 1920s (Box 99)
- Hand-sewn Chinese texts printed from hand-carved wooden printing blocks (Box 99)
- Notes, typescript drafts, and printed materials (by others) on Japanese military actions in China, some 1930s (Box 99)
- "Dictations of E P Lum, 9-13-34 to 10-3-34," notes (Box 99)
- Annual report of Tong Hai Tang (Pinyin transliteration), in Chinese with annotations in English, 1934 (Box 99)
- Bulletins, reports, and correspondence related to relief work in San Francisco, 1930s (Box 100)
- Case files on conditions of individuals and their families, with updates, holographic, 1930s, possibly related to Lowe's IPR survey work (Box 100)
- Datebook, 1935 (Box 100)
- Address books, undated (Box 100)
- Telephone directory of San Francisco Chinatown, in Chinese, 1933 (Box 100)
- "Interracial Relations - Chinese Efforts at Improving Relations" writing drafts and source clippings with annotations, 1920s-1930s (Box 101)
- Memorandum, reports, and other print material related to relief work in San Francisco, 1936-1938 (Box 101)
- Clipping related to Chinatown, 1960s (Box 101)
- China House Association of Berkeley files, 1955 (Box 101)
  Mainly consisting of correspondence
- Cultural Attaché files, 1963-1964 and undated. (Box 101)
  Mainly consisting of business cards and guestbooks, 1963-1964, as well as material related to Nursing Scholarship Opera Committee
- Guestbook, 1960-1964. (Box 102)
- Research notes, typescript and holographic (Box 102)
- Subject files related to San Francisco Chinatown and being Chinese American, 1930-1970s (Box 102)
  Including clippings, flyers, and programs
- Chinese telephone directory, San Francisco and Oakland, 1934 March (Box 102)
- Chinese Directory of San Francisco and East Bay, 1949 (Box 102)
  in English
- Printed Chinese textbooks, including book of English articles on President Lincoln translated into Chinese, 1945 (Box 102)
- Personal files related to apartment rentals, home furnishing, and recipes, and correspondence by Anita Lowe (Box 102)
- Subject files, 1930s-1970s (Box 103)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 103)
  - Writing drafts (Box 103)
  - "1950 November" and "1950 October," Research files consisting largely of clippings but also typescript drafts and notes. (Box 103)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 104)
  - Research files (Box 104)
  - Dissertation draft of section, covering events in Manchuria, 1947 January through June, 1953 (Box 104)
  - 1947 January (Box 104)
  - 1949 January-June (Box 104)
  - 1949 November (Box 104)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 105)
  - 1946 June-December (Box 105)
  - 1947 February-March (Box 105)
  - 1949 July-October (Box 105)
  - Related research material, 1950s (Box 105)
- Dissertation research and writing files, 1950s (Box 106)
  - 1946 February-May (Box 106)
  - 1947 April-1948 December (Box 106)
  - Czech language class notes, holographic and typescript, 1951 (Box 106)
- Subject files related to UNESCO, and particularly the 1968 Nairobi Conference (Box 106)
- Subject files on education relating to UNESCO, 1959-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 107-109)
- Harvard Club of the Republic of China administrative files, 1960s (Box 107-109)
- Harvard Business School Fund outgoing correspondence, 1959 (Box 107-109)
- Subject files, clippings and bulletins, 1970s (bulk 1979) (Box 110)
- Clippings and bulletins, 1978-1989 (bulk 1989) (Box 111)
- Subject files, 1978-1980s (Box 112-114.)
- Clippings, 1980s (Box 115)
- Subject files, 1980s (Box 116)
- Family history, accounting, and San Francisco Chinatown documents, 1920s-1940s, undated (Box 117)
  Mainly in Chinese
  - Description of family history, in Chinese, holographic, hand-sewn binding, undated (Box 117)
  - Account book, 1920s-1930s (Box 117)
    In Chinese, holographic
  - Fu Hua Company (pinyin) annual report, with holographic annotations, 1922 (Box 117)
  - Chinese Hospital San Francisco fundraising materials, probably 1920s (Box 117)
  - Yeung Wo Chinese School (Yang He) printed album, circa 1922 (Box 117)
  - Military service photo with holographic annotations, undated (Box 117)
- Dissertation research files, 1950s. (Box 118-124.)
  Typescript and holographic notes organized by author, by subject, and chronologically by historical period
- Chinese American history and sociology research files, 1930s, undated. (Box 125a-131.)
  Consists of draft writings and research files, including survey data, correspondence, ephemera, and clippings, in English and in Chinese
  - San Francisco Chinatown clippings, 1936 (Box 125a.)
    Includes articles from English-language newspapers outside of Chinatown concerning podii system of boycott in landlord-tenant disputes
  - Americanization. (Box 125a.)
    Includes topics of Chinatowns, Chinese Americans, interracial relationships, and sociological perspectives on culture change
  - Charity, religion (Box 125a.)
  - Economic activities (Box 125a.)
  - Religion, customs, charity, and recreation (Box 125a.)
  - Religion, customs, charity, and recreation (Box 125b.)
  - Imported skills and technology. (Box 125b.)
    Includes material related to skills and technology imported from China, and to import businesses
  - Non-Chinese consumption. (Box 125b.)
    Includes material related to Chinese businesses and industries
  - Medicine - Health (Box 125b.)
  - Health, 1930s, 1959, undated. (Box 125b.)
    Includes material related to health in Chinatowns, segregation, tuberculosis, and the plague scare of 1900
  - Economic Org. C. of C. [Chinese of California] (Box 125b.)
  - Immigration Laws (Box 125b.)
  - Population. (Box 125b.)
    Includes typescript notes on Chinatowns and Chinese American populations in Chico, Fresno, San Jose, San Rafael, and other smaller cities in California, 1930s
  - Population (Box 126a.)
  - Chinatowns (Box 126a.)
  - Immigration (Box 126a.)
  - Travel and transport (Box 126a.)
  - Early reception (Box 126a.)
  - Antagonism (racial discrimination) (Box 126a.)
  - Persecution (Box 126a.)
  - Prejudice - Exclusion (Box 126a.)
  - Chinafication (Box 126a.)
  - American-born Chinese (Box 126a.)
  - Improved interracial relations (Box 126a.)
  - Chinese consumption (Box 126a.)
  - Both races (Box 126a.)
  - American-born economic activities and opportunity (Box 126b.)
  - Economic activities (Box 126b.)
  - Respects, Attitudes and duties. (Box 126b.)
    Consists of notes regarding etiquette and traditional customs regarding relations with guests and among members of a family
  - District loyalties. (Box 126b.)
    Includes notes and draft writings about district associations and relations among them, including relations in central California among Chinese and Chinese American people from different districts
  - New code and ideals (Box 126b.)
  - Old holidays (Box 126b.)
  - New holidays (Box 126b.)
  - Smuggling of immigrants (Box 126b.)
  - Indifference. (Box 126b.)
    Consists mainly of notes and draft writings related to the attitudes of whites to Chinese and Chinese Americans, mainly in the U.S.
  - Favorable relationships (Box 127a)
  - Unfavorable relationships (Box 127a)
  - Organizations (Box 127a)
  - Six Companies. (Box 127a)
    Consists of notes and draft writings related to the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association, San Francisco, with some material related to Chicago and New York
  - Family organizations. (Box 127a)
    Consists mainly of notes and draft writings related to family associations
  - District organizations (Box 127a)
  - Tongs (Box 127a)
  - Special economic organizations. (Box 127a)
    Includes material related to the San Francisco Chinese Chamber of Commerce, merchants' associations and other specialized commercial associations, and the Chinese Hospital charity
  - Youth organizations (Box 127a)
  - Native-born organizations. (Box 127a)
    Includes material related to the Native Sons of the Golden State (Chinese American Citizens Alliance) and other Chinese American organizations
  - Older generation organizations (Box 127a)
  - Religious organizations (Box 127a)
  - Political organizations (Box 127a)
  - American organizations (Box 127a)
  - Crime and police (Box 127a)
  - Special pathological conditions (Box 127a)
  - Conclusions and hypotheses (Box 127a)
  - Methodology and bibliography (Box 127b.)
  - Sociological profiles and case studies files, 1930s. (Box 127b.)
    Includes typescript and holographic notes, with varying degrees of identification of individuals and their families, with relation to Oakland, Los Angeles, and San Francisco, California
  - Case study index card notes, holographic (Box 127b.)
  - Second generation (Box 127b.)
  - D. B. C., Dung Bo Choy (Box 127b.)
  - L. D. C. (Box 127b.)
  - L. W. C. (Box 127b.)
  - C. L., Miss, Mrs. W. C. L. (Box 127b.)
  - Children (Box 127b.)
  - L. L. (Box 127b.)
  - Dr. Ng Poon Chew (Box 127b.)
  - Ancestors (Box 127b.)
  - Yip Hay (Box 127b.)
  - Third Generation (Box 127b.)
  - Income (Box 127b.)
  - Housing and living conditions (Box 127b.)
  - Food and clothing (Box 127b.)
  - Food and clothing (Box 128a.)
  - Recreation and play (Box 128a.)
  - Kinship terms and names (Box 128a.)
  - Ancestor worship, rituals, religion (Box 128a.)
  - Chinese patriotism (Box 128a.)
  - China and Japanese war (Box 128a.)
  - Family (Box 128a.)
  - Birth, babyhood, and adoption (Box 128a.)
  - Sex, prostitution (Box 128a.)
  - Women's status (Box 128a.)
  - Marriage (Box 128a.)
  - Marriage (Box 128b)
  - Intermarriage (Box 128b)
  - Divorce (Box 128b)
  - Death (Box 128b)
  - Education (Box 128b)
  - Grammar school (Box 128b)
  - High school (Box 128b)
  - Colleges and Universities (Box 128b)
  - Language schools (Box 128b)
  - Chinese newspapers. Holographic and typescript notes concerning newspapers published in San Francisco and New York, currently and historically (Box 128b)
  - Customs and ideals (Box 129)
  - Family and clan authority. (Box 129)
    See also Family property, social rights
  - Family property, social rights (Box 129)
- American Commission for Relief in China organizing files, 1937-1938 and undated. (Box 129)
  Holographic notes related to building support in U.S. to raise funds to aid war-torn China
  - Chinese American history and sociology research files, 1930s, undated (Box 129)
  - Chinatown study organizing notes, 1937-1938 and undated. (Box 129)
    Includes typescript notes on organization of Chinatown Study report, people contacted, and notes related to research books checked out from the libraries,